Guide to the Sighle Kennedy papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Sighle Kennedy Papers,
circa 1920s-1996
[Bulk Dates: 1963-1996].
Kennedy, Sighle.
13.91 linear feet ( 21 document boxes, 2 note card boxes, 2 oversized boxes, 4 record boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
6340435
The majority of the Sighle Kennedy Papers consists of notes, research materials and drafts related to Kennedy’s scholarly work on Samuel Beckett’s novels, plays, and poetry. Most of this material was produced or gathered from the 1970s–1990s, during which Kennedy worked as a professor in the English department at Hunter College in New York City. The Papers contain correspondence between Kennedy and Beckett from 1967-1988, as well as two autograph letters from Beckett to his relative Harry Sinclair, one written in 1937 and one in 1938. The correspondence also includes letters Kennedy wrote to and received from other Beckett scholars. A small number of audio recordings (including gramophone records from the 1920s), several prints, including four by the Irish artist Jack Butler Yeats, and a number of annotated books complete this collection.
Biographical Note
Sighle Aileen Kennedy was born on 27 July 1919 in the United States to parents who had emigrated from Ireland in the first decade of the twentieth century. She received her undergraduate degree from Manhattanville College. After spending eight years as a reporter for an architectural and engineering journal, and twelve years working for Catholic Relief Services in countries including South Korea, Kennedy began graduate studies in English literature at Columbia University in 1963.
At Columbia, Kennedy was advised by Professor William York Tindall, whom she later honored with an essay in the festschrift Modern Irish Literature (1972). The notebook she kept while reading for her comprehensive exams (Box 2, Folder 1)--part study aid, part diary--shows Kennedy to have been a sensitive, insightful and enthusiastic reader of modern English-language literature, one who was drawn very early in her scholarly career to the writings of Samuel Beckett. Her first comments on Watt, the 1953 Beckett novel that would become her scholarly preoccupation for the next thirty years, reveal Kennedy to have been both horrified by (“His visions are explicitly disgusting. Dear old Ireland--what have we done to ourselves?”) and deeply interested in the book. Several entries in the notebook establish that Kennedy was a devout Catholic, one who took her religion seriously enough to question both her faith and behavior and the church as an institution. The diary also reveals the extent to which sexism pervaded academe in the era; one November 1963 entry briefly recounts a visit with a Columbia professor who, Kennedy reports, advised her that “teaching in a college... is something at which a woman is at a disadvantage.” Nevertheless, Kennedy pressed on, passed her exams, and moved on to the dissertation stage.
By 1966, Kennedy had decided to make Beckett's writings the subject of her doctoral study, and in 1969 she was awarded the Ph.D. after completing her dissertation, "Murphy's Bed: A Study of Real Sources and Sur-real Associations in Samuel Beckett's First Novel." The dissertation served as the first draft of her monograph, which was published in 1971 under the same title. Just before earning the Ph.D., Kennedy, ignoring her Columbia professor's advice, joined the faculty of Hunter College, one of the more prestigious institutions within the City University of New York system. She was an Assistant and then an Associate Professor in Hunter's English department from 1968-1985, teaching courses ranging from "Expository Writing," to "Women's Search for Self," to modern British literature surveys, to seminars on James Joyce and on Samuel Beckett.
In 1967, while working on her dissertation, Kennedy decided to write Beckett a letter related to her research on Murphy. Beckett answered, and he continued to answer her letters for the next twenty years, responding to her questions (to the extent that he ever answered anyone's questions about his writing) and giving her permission to reproduce selections from his unpublished manuscripts. During the early stages of her research for a planned monograph on Watt, Kennedy visited Paris, and met with Beckett for the first time in the summer of 1973. Though Kennedy's attitude towards Beckett was complicated--as would be the attitude of any scholar working with a living writer --the two appear to have gotten along well. Many of Beckett's letters to Kennedy reveal the warmth and generosity for which he was well known among friends and associates, but which was largely unsuspected by the reading public.
In the early 1970s, Kennedy decided that her second scholarly book would focus on Watt, and specifically on how the novel developed across the manuscript and typescript drafts. To that end, Kennedy traveled to libraries to gather material. The most important of these trips was her visit to the Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin, which holds the notebooks in which Beckett wrote his first draft of Watt as well as the typescript of his revised version. While Kennedy produced an outline of her book's proposed structure and arranged some of her research materials and notes accordingly, she was unable to complete the monograph. An article-length version of the work was posthumously published through the efforts of her sister, Sr. Ethne Kennedy (1922-2005), in Dalhousie French Studies in 1998.
While teaching and intermittently working on the Watt project, Kennedy also published several scholarly articles on Beckett and on the connections between his work and that of Joyce and Dante. She appears to have taught herself to read Italian so as to read Dante's writings in their original language. Her research materials show that Kennedy had become increasingly interested in Beckett's philosophical influences, including the 17th century Flemish thinker Arnold Geulincx and the 19th century German philosopher Arthur Schopenhauer.
After Sighle Kennedy's death on 18 August 1996, Sr. Ethne Kennedy (of the Society of Helpers) completed a preliminary organization of her sister's research materials and work-related correspondence. Her handwriting is visible on the covers of many of Sighle Kennedy's notebooks, and in many cases her descriptions of their contents have been retained in this finding aid. Very little purely personal material is included in this collection, though a reading of Kennedy's notes, drafts, letters and especially her notebook entries reveals much about the delight she found in, and the sustenance she drew from, literature during three decades which appear to have been almost totally devoted to reading, research and teaching.
Scope and Content
The Papers contain scholarly research-related materials gathered and/or produced by Sighle Kennedy during her years as a graduate student in Columbia University's English department (1963-1969) and as a professor at Hunter College (1968-1985). These materials consist of handwritten notes, note cards, drafts (autograph and typed), photocopies, photographs and annotated scholarly journals and books related to Kennedy's work on Samuel Beckett, with lesser amounts on Joyce, Dante, and other writers in whom Kennedy was interested. The collection also includes correspondence between Kennedy and Beckett; letters to and from and other Beckett scholars, academic and trade publishers, and special collections librarians; copies of several articles published by Kennedy, and her book, "Murphy's Bed". The Papers are completed by a small collection of audio materials used by Kennedy in her teaching; by a number of prints, including several by the Irish artist Jack Butler Yeats; and by four boxes of books annotated by Kennedy.
Arrangement
The Papers are arranged by medium and by genre. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by sender, while Kennedy’s notes, drafts, and journals are arranged chronologically. In series IV-VII, dates in parentheses refer to the date the text was first produced or published; the date upon which Kennedy photocopied and/or annotated the text is very often unknown.
Arranged in eight series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1937-1992 [Bulk Dates: 1967-1992]
Series II: Early Scholarly Work by Sighle Kennedy, 1963-1969
Series III: Scholarly Material for Projected Watt monograph, 1969-1996
Subseries 1: Watt Materials at the Humanities Research Center, University of Texas-Austin
Subseries 2: Watt Materials at Ohio State University, Washington Universityof St. Louis, the University of Reading, and Trinity College-Dublin
Subseries 3: Notes and Drafts for the Watt Monograph, undated
Subseries 4: Notes and Drafts for Watt Monograph, 1969-1997
Subseries 5: Assigned Research Material for Watt Monograph, undated
Subseries 6: Unassigned Research Material for Watt Monograph, undated
Series IV: Scholarly Material for Related Projects on Beckett, circa 1978-1996
Subseries 1: Beckett and Arnold Geulincx, 1985-1989
Subseries 2: Beckett and Dante, 1980-1996
Subseries 3: Beckett and James Joyce, 1978-1989
Subseries 4: Scholarly Material on Other Writing by Beckett, 1929-1983
Subseries 5: Notes and Research Material on Samuel Beckett, general, 1934-1996
Series V: Other Scholarly and Beckett-related Printed Material, 1970-1996
Series VI: Published Scholarly Writing by Sighle Kennedy, 1970-1990
Subseries 1: Conference Papers and Proposals, 1979-1986
Subseries 2: Published Articles, Book Reviews, and Monograph, 1970-1990
Series VII: Audio and Visual Material, circa 1920s-1986
Subseries 1: Audio Cassette Tapes, 1966-1986
Subseries 2: Records --LP and Gramophone, circa 1920s-1966
Subseries 3: Visual Art and Related Material, undated
Subseries 4: Photographs, 1963-1974
Series VIII: Books Annotated by Sighle Kennedy
Subseries 1: Books by Samuel Beckett in French
Subseries 2: Books by Samuel Beckett in English
Subseries 3: Books about Samuel Beckett
Subseries 4: Books about James Joyce
Subseries 5: Translations of Books by Dante
Subseries 6: Books about Dante or Related to Kennedy’s Dante Project
Subseries 7: Other Books
Subjects
Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989--Correspondence.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989--Criticism and interpretation.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989--Dramatic works.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989--Fiction.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989--Manuscripts--Facsimiles.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989.--Murphy.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989.--Watt.; Colum, Padraic, 1881-1972.; Ellmann, Richard, 1918-1987.; Fletcher, John, 1937-; Geulincx, Arnold, 1624-1669.; Gilvarry, James, 1914-; Gontarski, S. E.; Harvey, Lawrence E., 1925-; Joyce, James, 1882-1941.; Joyce, James, 1882-1941--Criticism and interpretation.; Kennedy, Sighle.; Knowlson, James.; Leventhal, A. J. (Abraham Jacob), 1896-1979.; Lindon, Jérôme, 1925-2001.; O'Brien, Eoin.; Pilling, John.; Schechner, Richard, 1934-; Yeats, Jack Butler, 1871-1957.; Drama--20th century--History and criticism.; Fiction--20th century--History and criticism.; French literature--20th century.; French literature--20th century--History and criticism.; Irish literature--20th century.; Irish literature--20th century--History and criticism.; Universities and colleges--United States--Faculty.; Universities and colleges--New York (State); Women--Education (Higher)--United States.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Reading Room. Please consult the Rare Book and Manuscript Library for further information.
Acquisition
Sr. Ethne Kennedy, Donation, 1997.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1937-1992 [Bulk Dates: 1967-1992]
  This series primarily consists of letters written to and from Kennedy during her scholarly career. Kennedy kept carbon copies of many of her own letters, including those she wrote to Samuel Beckett. (Kennedy had pasted her letters to Beckett in a protective binder, from which they have been removed and which left their pages striped by glue.) Other correspondents include: Mary Doll, Richard Ellman, John Fletcher, James Gilvarry, Stanley E. Gontarski, Lawrence E. Harvey, John Kelly, James Knowlson, A.J. Leventhal, Jérôme Lindon (of Les Éditions de Minuit, Beckett’s French publisher), George O. Marshall, Jr., W. Kelly Morris and Richard Schechner (of the Tulane Drama Review), Eoin T. O’Brien, John Pilling, and representatives of the Columbia, Dartmouth, Ohio State, Texas, and Washington University Libraries, of the Modern Language Association, and scholarly publishers the Associated University Press, Bucknell University Press, and Princeton University Press. Of note are the letters from TDR’s Morris and editor Schechner (later a professor at New York University and a major figure in the field of performance studies); they are two very harsh critiques of Kennedy’s first journal article attempt. That Kennedy, then still a graduate student, kept the letters is illustrative of her character.
  Also present in this series are two autograph letters from Beckett to his uncle’s brother, Harry Sinclair, one written in October 1937 and one dated 2 February 1938, and one photocopy of a typed letter draft, in German, from Beckett to his friend Axel Kaun, dated 9 July 1937. The Sinclair letters were written during the time of the libel suit (eventually successful) brought against the Irish writer, politician, physician and wit Oliver St. John Gogarty for his portrayal of the Sinclair family in his 1937 memoir As I Was Going Down Sackville Street. Beckett’s affidavit in the case was taken on 12 May 1937. The second letter reports on the status of Beckett’s health following his hospitalization for a stab wound to his lung given to him on 7 January 1938 by a Parisian pimp, apparently for no reason. Beckett wrote the letter from the Hotel Liberia in Paris, where he was convalescing.
  - Associated University Press, 1970-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Beckett, Samuel to Axel Kaun (copy of draft), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Beckett, Samuel, to Harry Sinclair, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beckett, Samuel to Sighle Kennedy, 1967-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1986-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Doll, Mary, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ellman, Richard, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fell, Cynthia (Associated/Bucknell University Press), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fletcher, John, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gilvarry, James, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gontarski, Stanley E., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hall, Holly (Washington University Libraries), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Harvey, Lawrence E., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Humanities Research Center, University of Texas-Austin, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Kelly, John,1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Kennedy, Sighle to Samuel Beckett, 1967-1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kennedy, Sighle, 1965-1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kennedy, Sighle, 1977-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Knowlson, James, 1974-1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Leventhal, A.J., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Library Chronicle of the University of Texas-Austin, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lindon, Jérôme, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Mackesy, Eileen (Modern Language Association), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Marshall, George O., Jr., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Morris, W. Kelly (Tulane Drama Review), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Mortimer, Roger (Washington University Libraries), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - O'Brien, Eoin T., 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Pilling, John, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Princeton University Press, 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Schechner, Richard (Tulane Drama Review), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Tibbetts, Robert A. (Ohio State University Libraries), 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Wright, Walter W. (Dartmouth College Library), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series II: Early scholarly work by Sighle Kennedy, 1963-1969
  Located here is the scholarly work that Kennedy produced while in graduate school at Columbia University, including notebooks Kennedy filled while studying for her comprehensive exams, a typed carbon copy of her dissertation proposal, a leather-bound copy of her dissertation, and early drafts and a final copy of an unpublished 1966 article entitled “An Obscure Key to Waiting for Godot” (see Box 1, Folders 25 and 30 in the Correspondence series for letters related to this article).
  - Notes on reading for comprehensive exams, 1963 October-1964 March (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "An Obscure Key to Waiting for Godot," typescript drafts, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Conrad's Looking-Glass World: The Forecastle of the NARCISSUS." Circa 1965. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ph. D. dissertation proposal, 1966 June (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Murphy's Bed: A Study of Real Sources and Sure-real Associations in Samuel Beckett's First Novel. Ph.D. dissertation, Columbia University, 1969. (Box 2)
- Series III: Scholarly material for projected Watt monograph, 1969-1996
  This series contains materials gathered and produced by Kennedy during the long period in which she researched and drafted what she hoped would be a monograph on Beckett’s development of Watt from manuscript to publication. Photocopies of literary and scholarly writings — here called “research materials” — have been separated from Kennedy’s loose notes, notebooks and drafts. Many of the research materials are annotated by Kennedy.
  - Subseries III.1: Watt materials at the Humanities Research Center, University of Texas-Austin
    The research materials include lightly annotated photocopies of Beckett’s manuscript notebooks and typescripts for Watt. Kennedy’s initial notes on the materials are also placed here.
    - Photocopy of Watt manuscript notebook I (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Photocopy of Watt manuscript notebook II (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Photocopy of Watt manuscript notebook III (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Photocopy of Watt manuscript notebook IV (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Photocopy of Watt manuscript notebook IV insert (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Photocopy of Watt manuscript notebook V (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Photocopy of Watt manuscript notebook VI (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Photocopy of Watt manuscript notebook, "Revision of Watt, section 1" (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Photocopy of Watt typescript, Part I, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Photocopy of Watt typescript, Part II, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - Photocopies of Watt manuscripts and typescript (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Sighle Kennedy's notes on HRC Watt materials (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries III.2: Watt and other Beckett materials at other universities
    This small subseries contains photocopied excerpts of the Beckett materials housed at OSU and Washington U. — the Watt galleys, the manuscripts and typescripts of Happy Days and That Time — and Kennedy’s notes on them. Also included here are photocopies of catalogues listing Reading’s and TCD’s Beckett holdings.
    - Photocopies of Watt materials at Ohio State University (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Photocopies of Happy Days and That Time manuscripts and typescripts at OSU (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Sighle Kennedy's notes on OSU Beckett materials (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Photocopy of Watt galleys at Washington University-St. Louis (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Photocopies of catalogues of Beckett materials at University of Reading and Trinity College Dublin (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Subseries III.3: Notes and drafts for the Watt monograph, undated
    Contained in this subseries are the notes and drafts Kennedy assigned to specific sections of the projected monograph. The sections, which are designated by a combination of roman numerals and letters, correspond to her outline (Folder 1). Notes and drafts not assigned to a specific section are located afterward. An undated draft of a scholarly article related to this project, “A Hidden Passage in the History of Samuel Beckett’s Art: His Early Notebooks of Watt,” completes this grouping.
    - Outline for Kennedy's projected monograph on Watt, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Notes and drafts for introduction, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Notes and drafts, Section Ib, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Notes and drafts, Sections Ic and Ie, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Notes and drafts, Section Id, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Notes and drafts, Section IIa, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Notes and drafts, Section IIb, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Notes and drafts, Section IIc, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Notes and drafts, Section IId, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Notes and drafts, Section IIe, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Notes and drafts, section unassigned, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
    - Notes and drafts, section unassigned, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Draft of scholarly article on Watt: "A Hidden Passage in the History of Samuel Beckett's Art: His Early Notebooks of Watt," undated. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Subseries III.4: Notes and drafts for Watt monograph, 1969-1996
    Subseries 4 includes dated notebooks, loose notes and drafts Kennedy wrote while working on the Watt project. The notebooks occasionally feature revealing diary-style entries on a number of topics, which range from her first meeting with Beckett in Paris (in the summer of 1973), to her attitude toward the Irish writer and toward her own scholarly work and abilities. The drafts show Kennedy’s intensive revision process; she heavily annotated, rearranged and reworked passages multiple times. This group of material also contains two further drafts of a long essay version of the Watt monograph, one dated 1982 and one submitted posthumously by Kennedy’s sister, Sr. Ethne Kennedy, in 1997 (it is dated here 1996 because this is the latest version of the draft extant in Kennedy’s files upon her death that year).
    - Notebook containing diary entries, letter drafts, and notes on Watt project, 1969-1974 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Notes on visit to Paris and first meeting with Beckett, 1973 June-August (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Notes on interview with Henry Wenning, 1973 September (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Note (incomplete), 1973 October (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Notebook containing diary entries and drafts, 1975 August-1976 March (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Loose notes and notebook, 1976 June-July (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Loose notes and notebook, 1977 January-March (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Loose notes, notebook, and diary entries, 1979 July-December (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Loose notes and notebook, 1980 February (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Notes and drafts, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Notes and drafts, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Typescript draft of "'Astride of a Grave and a Difficult Birth': Samuel Beckett's Watt Struggles to Life," 1982 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Notebook, 1983 November (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Notes and drafts, 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Notes and drafts, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Notebook containing notes and diary entries, 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Loose notes, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Notebook, 1988-1990 "Notes resuming on Watt notebooks" (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Full typescript of "'Astride of a Grave and a Difficult Birth': Samuel Beckett's Watt Struggles to Life," 1996 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Subseries III.5: Assigned research material for Watt monograph, undated